Archit Jain

Software Engineer | Backend Engineer | FullStack Engineer

Email: archiitjaih@gmail.com LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/archit-jain-you Mobile: +91-8107212111
Portfolio: architjain128.github.io Github: github.com/Architjain128

Summary

Software engineer with over 2 years of experience in C++, C, and backend development. Experienced in building distributed, high-availability scalable systems, optimizing concurrency, and improving memory efficiency. Worked extensively on real-time media servers in C for CPaaS solution. Strong background in system design, deployment, and solving performance challenges to deliver reliable solutions.

SKILLS SUMMARY

• Languages: JAVA, C, C++, JavaScript, Python, GO

• Frameworks: SpringBoot, NodeJS, OpenGL, React, NextJS, Redux, Express, Django, Opentelemetry, Flutter

• Databases: MongoDb, Redis, MySQL

• Technologies: Kafka, Elasticsearch, Docker, Kubernetes

EXPERIENCE

Product Engineer - Sprinklr

July 2023 - Present

- Developed a high-performance VoIP telephony platform, enabling a customer-to-agent call system handling 1M+ daily calls with a highly scalable architecture.
- Optimized system performance, increasing VoIP call capacity from 50 to 800+ per instance by fixing memory leaks and enhancing CPU efficiency with proper nested locking and thread handling optimization in the **media server in C**.
- Reduced MongoDB query load using indexing, integrated Redis caching, and implemented auto-scaling of media servers based on real-time VoIP traffic, leading to infrastructure cost savings.
- Integrated Kafka and Elasticsearch for **real-time monitoring**, **reporting**, **and alerting** in a distributed telephony system; collaborated on automated testing pipelines and stress testing for microservices.
- Led customer onboarding, and resolved 80% of client issues same-day, ensuring VoIP platform stability, high availability, and seamless operations.

Software Development Engineer - Speedlegal

Dec 2022 - June 2023

- Designed and developed an AI-powered legal contract management platform using the **MERN stack** to analyze, manage, and share contracts across internal teams and external users.
- Contributed to platform development, focusing on system architecture and database design. Implemented key features like document parsing, editing, AI chatbot, automated summaries, and a structured file management system.
- o Delivered on-demand client features rapidly to meet business requirements efficiently.

Software Development Engineer Intern - JIO Platforms Ltd

May 2022 – July 2022

- Built features for a React-based healthcare platform, fixed production bugs and integrated Google Analytics to enhance performance and capture user experience based on business requirements.
- Built a Flutter mobile app with drag-and-drop functionality, custom component reordering, and complex graph rendering to predict and analyze the playing XI performance for a cricket match.

EDUCATION

International Institute of Information Technology

Hyderabad, India

Bachelor of Technology - Computer Science and Technology; GPA: 8.21

July 2019 - June 2023

Courses: Operating Systems, Data Structures, Distributed Systems, Design and Analysis of Software Systems, Statistical Methods in AI, Information Retrieval and Extraction, Advanced Computer Networks, Database and Application

PROJECTS

• Wikipedia Search Engine - Python

A scalable search and indexing engine for Wikipedia dump converts it to an inverted index of 1/5th of its size. It further processes the index to return top matching results for any search query based on the tf-idf score. It also supports field queries.

• Multithreading Simulation - C

Developed a simulation of vaccine production by multiple companies with varying effectiveness, supplying vaccines to different zones of the campus on-demand to vaccinate randomly arriving students in real time.

• Linux Shell - C

A command-line interface based on the Unix Bash shell. Supports multiple commands per line, signal handling, chained redirection, piping, foreground and background process.

ACHIEVEMENTS

• JEE Main 2019 - AIR 128

- \bullet JEE Advanced 2019 AIR 2128
- Google Kick Start 2022 574th Rank

Volunteer Experience

- Teaching Assistant IIIT Hyderabad Teaching Assistant for Discrete Structure course.
- Astronomy Club Coordinator IIIT Hyderabad Organising and managing various club events.